<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of Samuel White humbly presented to the honourable, the knights, citizens, and burgesses, in Parliament assembled.</title>
            <author>White, Samuel, ca. 1650-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20548</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12259222</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12259222</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57767</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35640)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57767)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 176:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of Samuel White humbly presented to the honourable, the knights, citizens, and burgesses, in Parliament assembled.</title>
                  <author>White, Samuel, ca. 1650-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>168-?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Samuel White.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>White, Samuel, ca. 1650-1689.</term>
               <term>East India Company.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57767:1"/>
            <head>THE Caſe of Samuel White <hi>Humbly Preſented,</hi> To the Honourable, the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, in Parliament Aſſembled.</head>
            <p>I Went to <hi>India, Anno</hi> 75. as Mate on board the Ship <hi>Loyal Subject,</hi> Captain <hi>William Goodlad</hi> Commander, for the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> Company; and did with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and conſent of the <hi>Governour</hi> of <hi>Fort</hi> St. <hi>George,</hi> and by leave of the foreſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander remain in <hi>India,</hi> giving ſecurity to indempnifie the ſaid Commander, from the penalty of one Hundred Pounds, he was lyable to pay for any Perſon ſo left behind him, which being accordingly exacted by the Company at the Ships return, was duly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd by my Correſpondent here.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>George White</hi> my Brother, did at this time reſide in the Kingdom of <hi>Syam,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at his Invitation I remov'd, and voyaging ſoon after to <hi>Metchlepatam,</hi> it happened in time of my being there, that the King of <hi>Syam</hi>'s <hi>Agent</hi> applied himſelf to the Chief of the Companies Factory, for a Perſon well qualified, to navigate a Ship of the Kings, betwixt that place, and the Port of <hi>Mergen:</hi> To which employ he was pleas'd to recommend me, and I continued therein about four years, being ſo happy to have my ſervices well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by the ſaid <hi>Kings Miniſters,</hi> and by them ſo favourably repreſented to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> that he was graciouſly pleaſed, to let me in a large meaſure partake of his <hi>Royal</hi> Bounty and favour.</p>
            <p>In this Interim, Mr. <hi>Conſtant Phaulkon,</hi> who ſometime had his dependence on my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers friendſhip, was become very conſiderable in the Court of <hi>Syam;</hi> as he has ſince by his great merit, rais'd himſelf to be the <hi>Prime Miniſter,</hi> having all Important Affairs of the Kingdom entirely under his Charge and Conduct: and by his kind aſſiſtance, I was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd to another employment, much more advantageous; being made <hi>Shawbander</hi> of <hi>Tenaſſary</hi> and <hi>Mergen,</hi> whereby I was entruſted with the Collecting and managing all the <hi>Kings</hi> revenues in that <hi>Province,</hi> and was likewiſe <hi>Chief Commiſſioner</hi> for his Maritime Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, of which my preferment I delayed not to give notice to my friends in the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ſervice at <hi>Fort</hi> St. <hi>George, Metchlepatam</hi> and <hi>Bengall,</hi> humbly tendring my beſt ſervices to their Commands, in whatever I might be uſeful to the Publick or their private Concerns, and they were pleaſed to return me their kind Congratulations, and give me ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of ſerving them. Nor was it long after my being raiſ'd to this Capacity, that there did preſent a ſuitable opportunity to teſtifie my <hi>Zeal</hi> to the Companies Service; for their Ship the <hi>Golden Fleece,</hi> in her return from <hi>Bengall</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> ſprung a deſperate Leake, in which diſtreſs the only near and commodious Port that preſented for their relief was <hi>Mergen,</hi> whither in confidence of my friendly aſſiſtance they came, and found me as ready to grant, as they could be to requeſt, all that my intereſt and influence there could afford them, in my giving them the uſe of my own Slaves for the more expeditious unlading their Ship, ſecuring their Goods in Warehouſes aſhore, and aſſiſting the relading thereof with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt Charge, when the Ship was refitted to proceed on her Voyage, for which I alſo ſupplied them with whatever they wanted at the very ſame rates the <hi>King</hi> himſelf paid, and wholly excuſed them from all the duties of the Port. But I need not particularize how fully I anſwer'd or rather exceeded their expectations in all things, or call any other Teſtimony for proof thereof, than the report made here at home by Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>James Cook</hi> the <hi>Commander,</hi> who was ſo ſenſible of my good deſervings on this occaſion, that he very earneſtly ſolicited the Committee for ſome ſignification of their kind accepting thoſe my conſiderable Services. But an over-ruling power amongſt them, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered this grateful motion ineffectual; however I am not the leſs pleas'd, that I had the good fortune to be Inſtrumental in ſecuring and forwarding ſo great a Concern as that was, which I underſtand did here produce no leſs than 190000. l.</p>
            <p>It was now the beginning of the Year 84. when I received orders from the <hi>Court of Syam,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57767:2"/>to ſit out ſeveral Ships for proſecuting the War againſt the <hi>Kings of Golcondah and Pegu,</hi> as by the ſame Command I alſo did the ſucceeding year, in which expeditions I muſt own, we were very much befriended by the Preſident and Council of <hi>Fort</hi> St. <hi>George,</hi> who ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied us with Ammunition and Naval Stores, and accommodated us with ſome <hi>Engliſh men</hi> for thoſe occaſions, nor were they wanting to congratulate our ſucceſſes, and make large proffers of their readineſs, to give us further aſſiſtance, as appears by their general Letters, both to my <hi>Lord Phaulkon,</hi> and my ſelf: while on the other ſide, there was all poſſible care taken by the <hi>King</hi>'s ſpecial Command, that not the leaſt injury or offence ſhould be done to the Company, or any under their protection, as was ſtrictly enjoin'd in the Commiſſion to every Commander; and accordingly amongſt many ſmaller Veſſels, two Conſiderable Ships that were taken at <hi>Pegu,</hi> and brought into <hi>Mergen,</hi> tho they appeared to belong to the Inhabitants of <hi>Mechlepatam,</hi> yet upon producing <hi>Engliſh</hi> Paſports were without further trouble diſcharged.</p>
            <p>In this good accord ſtood the Correſpondence betwixt the <hi>King of Syam and our Company</hi> to all appearance, when in <hi>April</hi> 87. we were ſurpriſ'd with the ſtrange News that Captain <hi>Nicholſon,</hi> Admiral of the Companies Fleet in <hi>Bengall,</hi> had there ſeized on a Ship of the <hi>King of Syams,</hi> called the <hi>Revenge,</hi> Commanded by Captain <hi>Edward Engliſh,</hi> who then came from <hi>Fort</hi> St. <hi>George,</hi> where he had been kindly received and ſupplied with Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Men for the <hi>Kings</hi> ſervice, and theſe ill tidings were ſoon followed, by the like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, concerning a <hi>Sloop,</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> called the <hi>Mary,</hi> taken by Captain <hi>Battin,</hi> in the <hi>Rebecca,</hi> at the <hi>Port</hi> of <hi>Pudicherry,</hi> about which time, I alſo receiv'd Letters from my friends at <hi>Fort</hi> St. <hi>George,</hi> acquainting me that the Company had ſent out poſitive or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, for making War upon the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam:</hi> Of all which, I did (as my duty obliged me) immediately diſpatch advices to my <hi>Lord Phaulkon,</hi> and the <hi>Privy Council,</hi> humbly Offering it as my opinion, that ſince we well knew this undeſerved rupture muſt be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by the malicious miſreports of ſome, who were in that regard no leſs Enemies to their own Countries Honour, and welfare, than the Affairs of <hi>Syam;</hi> and that againſt all the Rules of Juſtice, and Law of Nations, theſe acts of Hoſtility were committed, before any Cauſe aſſign'd, by making complaint, and demanding ſatisfaction. It would therefore be convenient, that his <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Syam</hi> employ'd ſome fitting Perſon to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> to give him a true account of theſe unkind uſages, and endeavour to renew and corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate that Correſpondence, which his <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>Syam</hi> had in ſo many inſtances mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his intention, and deſire to conſerve with the <hi>Engliſh Nation. My Lord Phaulkon</hi> and the <hi>Council,</hi> made their applications to the <hi>King,</hi> concerning this motion of mine, who was pleaſ'd not only to approve thereof, but alſo to do me the Honour of nominating me, to ſerve him in that occaſion: and becauſe there was then no Ship of the <hi>Kings</hi> in <hi>Port,</hi> ſo proper for the Voyage, as this of my own, whereon I afterwards eſcap'd with my Life; I had orders to fit her, and my ſelf, with all expedition, and be in readineſs to proceed upon receipt of Letters from <hi>Court;</hi> with conſiderable Preſents to the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Royal Conſort,</hi> which were diſpatching towards me, and had certainly come to hand in twenty days time, had not the ſudden fatal change of things, after the arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of Captain <hi>Weltden</hi> in the <hi>Curtana,</hi> not only prevented that deſign, but occaſioned the <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of about ſixty of my Country Men on that Place: I only by a Miracle of Mercy, being left to bring the ſad account of that bloudy Tragedy, which I am ready to repreſent when this Honourable Houſe ſhall be pleaſ'd to command it.</p>
            <p>And now I am come to that unhappy Period when thoſe heavy Calamities began to fall upon me, which have brought me to ruin, and deſolation. For at the time I fled aboard my Ship to ſave my Life, I left behind me 21877. l. which I had at that Place in ſundry effects, as I can prove by an exact account of the particulars upon my Oath, having alſo the Teſtimony of other credible Perſons, for the greater part thereof, and under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent circumſtances of the War our Company has been pleas'd to make with the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam,</hi> I have too much reaſon to deſpair of retrieving any thing of it: but this was yet but a part of the ſevere perſecution I have ſuffered; for while I was under theſe diſaſters at the place of my Reſidence, my other conſiderable Concerns that were abroad in Trade, were made a Prey, by the Companies Servants, which is more particularly my preſent complaint, and I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn a true account thereof as follows.</p>
            <p>In the foreſaid Sloop <hi>Mary</hi> taken by Captain <hi>Battin,</hi> I Shipp'd ſixty Cheſts of Copper, for my proper account, conſigned to <hi>Monſr. Delandres,</hi> ſecond of the <hi>French</hi> Factory at <hi>Pudicherry,</hi> which the Gentlemen at <hi>Fort</hi> St. <hi>George</hi> were pleaſ'd to condemn in their Court, and confiſcate to the Companies uſe; wherein I firſt accuſe them of the groſſeſt injuſtice, for they might if they had pleaſed, have been ſatisfied of my Property, in thoſe Goods by the bill of Lading, which was produc'd in their Court in my behalf, and not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57767:3"/>only at the time when I Shipp'd that Concern, but alſo when the Veſſel was taken, there was no War declared with <hi>Syam,</hi> and therefore with what legal pretence, they could lay claim to thoſe Goods of mine, I leave to the judgment of all impartial Perſons in the World. But I am further alſo to accuſe them, of the baſeſt Ingratitude to me, who had in the like caſe deſerv'd much more friendly dealing from them; for in the preceding year, when one of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam</hi>'s Men of War, brought a Prize into <hi>Mergen,</hi> belonging to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of <hi>Golcondah,</hi> and in the examination of the Cargo, I found ſundry Goods to a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable amount that appear'd to belong to Mr. <hi>Robert Freeman</hi> the Companies Chief at <hi>Metchlepatam,</hi> I ſecur'd them for him, and remitted them to the Preſident, and Council at <hi>Fort</hi> St. <hi>George,</hi> as I can prove by their own acknowledgment, and this my kindneſs they were pleaſed ſo ſoon after to gratifie in ſeizing my aforeſaid Copper to the amount of 400 l.</p>
            <p>The next thing I complain of is, concerning an Adventure I had on board the <hi>Derreah Dowlett,</hi> a Ship of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Syam</hi>'s, which by order from Court, I laded with ſundry Merchandiſes and diſpatch'd for <hi>Acheen,</hi> having alſo liberty to lade on her a conſiderable quantity of <hi>Rice,</hi> and <hi>Liquors</hi> for my own account, which I conſigned to <hi>William Mallett,</hi> my Servant; whom I ſent on the ſame bottom, and they were no ſooner arrived at <hi>Port,</hi> and began to diſpoſe of the Cargo in <hi>April,</hi> 87. but Captain <hi>Conſett</hi> came thither in the <hi>Berkly Caſtle,</hi> wearing his <hi>Majeſties Colours,</hi> and took the ſaid Ship, and tho my Factor did then manifeſt unto him my aforeſaid Concern by Invoice and Orders, and made demand accordingly; yet would he not be prevailed with, to reſtore the leaſt part thereof, but vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently ſeized on all, whereby I am damnified, the amount of 1838 l. as beſides my own Oath, I can prove by the Teſtimony of others; At the ſame time and place, the ſaid Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Conſett</hi> took alſo a Ship of mine, then riding in that Road, under the Enſign of our <hi>Nation</hi> called the <hi>Succeſs</hi> of about 100 Tuns burthen, and tho the Maſter <hi>Caleb Tracy,</hi> did make appear by my Commiſſion to him that ſhe belonged to me, yet was he not pleaſ'd to take the leaſt notice thereof, but Seiz'd and carried her with him to <hi>Bengall,</hi> which Ship coſt me ſet to Sea 450 l.</p>
            <p>My next, and greateſt Article of this kind, is concerning my Ship <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> burthen about 350 Tuns, which in <hi>January</hi> 87. I diſpatched with a Cargo, to <hi>Mocah</hi> in the <hi>Red Seas,</hi> the Prime Coſt of ſtock and block amounting to 7800 l. which I ſolemnly affirm did entirely belong to my ſelf; She arrived in ſafety at her <hi>Port,</hi> the 20. of <hi>April,</hi> where having delivered her Cargo aſhore to my Factor, Mr. <hi>William How,</hi> the Ship was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Order, ſent to a place about five Leagues diſtant to take in a quantity of Salt, while my Factor was making ſale of my Goods; but on the 25. of <hi>May,</hi> Captain <hi>Andrews,</hi> in the Ship <hi>Charles the Second,</hi> arriv'd there in the equipage of an Admiral of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> Fleet, wearing the union Flagg at the Main Topmaſt head, and firſt he ſent his Barge aſhore with ſeveral armed Men, to ſeize Mr. <hi>How,</hi> and the <hi>Purſer</hi> Mr. <hi>Wortly,</hi> as they did, and carried them Priſoners aboard his Ship, where at firſt ſight of Captain <hi>Andrews,</hi> Mr. <hi>How</hi> deliver'd him a Letter from me directd to the Commanders of any of the Companies Ships he ſhould happen to meet with, in which I ſignified my Property in the aforeſaid Ship and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, and humbly requeſted their aſſiſtance and friendſhip, as occaſion might require. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of exerciſing any ſuch humanity towards them or me, he not only detained them his Priſoners, but went himſelf aſhore, to take poſſeſſion of my Eſtate, entring the Houſe wherein my Goods were lodg'd in a ſort of Triumph. For he did himſelf the Honour to have the <hi>King</hi>'s Flagg carried before him, which he afterwards fix'd upon the Houſe, and having thus made himſelf Lord and Maſter of my Goods, he ſent two Boats with armed Men, in ſearch of my Ship, which they ſoon found out, and tho there was not the leaſt reſiſtance made, by the uſe of any Weapons, nor any other defence, ſave the Mens ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves into their cloſe quarters, yet at the firſt entring of my Ship, they fired thirty or forty Piſtols, and therewith mortally wounded the Maſter Mr. <hi>William Rand,</hi> whom with the reſt they carried Priſoner on board the <hi>Charles the Second,</hi> where after Nine days languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he dyed, and was uſed by Captain <hi>Andrews</hi> with that barbarous cruelty, that his ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt requeſt of but having a friend admitted to ſpeak with him, a few hours before he expired, was denied him. The Commander being thus Murthered, and the Ship taken, Captain <hi>Andrews</hi> goes on to do what he thought fit with my Goods, converting ſome to his own uſe, ſelling ſome at <hi>Mocah,</hi> and carrying the reſt to <hi>Bombay,</hi> where at his arrival he firſt paies his Hommage to the <hi>General</hi> Sr. <hi>John Child,</hi> by making a preſent to his <hi>Lady</hi> out of his ſpoils being ſeveral of my large <hi>China Jars,</hi> And ſome time after he had thus begun to do Execution, they go on to the tryal and condemnation of my Ship and Goods in their Court of Admiralty, where (his <hi>Excellency the General</hi> having turn'd out <hi>Dr.</hi> St <hi>John,</hi> who was Commiſſion'd by the late <hi>King Charles</hi>) Sr. <hi>John Weyborn</hi> the Deputy Governour of the <hi>Iſland,</hi> did by the Generals Commiſſion ſit in the place of Judg, and had for his Mates <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57767:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Simpſon</hi> the Miniſter, and <hi>Henry Thruſtcroſs</hi> a Factor, which I muſt by the way obſerve, was an open violation and contempt of the very Charter, whereon they ground their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Authority, for erecting that Court; For the ſaid Charter which by their great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt with ſome of the Miniſters of State, they obtained in the year 83. does expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that it conſiſts of a Perſon learned in the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> and two Merchants, whereas Sr. <hi>John Weyborn</hi> was bred a Sailor, <hi>Patrick Simpſon</hi> is a <hi>Scotch Parſon,</hi> and <hi>Henry Thruſtcroſs</hi> a <hi>Native</hi> of <hi>India,</hi> all of them wholly Ignorant in the <hi>Civil Laws,</hi> but they prov'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves nevertheleſs ſufficient to ſerve this turn. For when they were ſet up, Captain <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> firſt exhibited a Libel to them, alledging the Ship to belong to the <hi>King of Syam,</hi> and it was very induſtriouſly endeavoured both by the General and him, that they ſhould find it ſo, in hopes that by its paſſing for the Concern of a Prince whom they call'd their Enemy, it would both help to ſtifle the loud outcrys of the Commander's Blood, and alſo give them a ſurer Title to their Prize, but the Men of my Ship continued all ſtedfaſt in affirming that I was the ſole Proprietor, to the beſt of their knowledge, (altho I am able to prove that one of them was tempted by a conſiderable Bribe to have declared the contrary) by which this ſtratagem fell to the Ground, tho his <hi>Excellency</hi> expreſs'd his diſpleaſure againſt his <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of his <hi>Admiralty</hi> for diſappointing him therein; But however they were reſolv'd by ſome means or other to compaſs their ends; for upon this diſappointment, Captain <hi>Andrews</hi> caus'd the firſt Libel to be withdrawn, and contrary to the common ſtile of all ſuch Courts was ſuffer'd to prefer another, declaring the Ship and Goods to belong to me; but muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs be made a Prize in regard ſhe had not a Paſs from ſome of the Companies Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: <hi>For the General who declares he has <hi>Deſpotick Power and Sovereign Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> in his breaſt would have it ſo, and his Judges obey'd his Voice;</hi> tho it ſeems their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces gave them a Check whilſt they were paſſing that cruel and unjuſt Condemnation, by raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome doubts among them of the Validity of that Reaſon to confiſcate my Eſtate, which caus'd them to ſubjoin a Clauſe to their illegal and errroneous Sentence, declaring that tho the Ship and Goods were now condemn'd as mine, yet if any part thereof ſhould after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards appear to belong to the King of <hi>Syam</hi> or his Subjects it ſhould be condemn'd accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; And thus by the depredation begun by Captain <hi>Andrews</hi> at <hi>Mocah,</hi> and finiſh'd by the <hi>General</hi>'s <hi>Deſpotick Power and Sovereign Authority</hi> at <hi>Bombay,</hi> I have had the amount of 7800 <hi>l.</hi> principal Money moſt unjuſtly and violently taken from me; And I am ſure I do my ſelf wrong in charging them with no greater Sum than 8000 <hi>l.</hi> more for the Advance which that Adventure would have render'd me. Nor muſt I here forget that the Poor Men belonging to my Ship had no better quarter given them for their ſmall matters, for when in moſt humble manner they petition'd his <hi>Excellency</hi> the <hi>General,</hi> that he would be ſo gracious to Conſider 'em for their Wages, and permit 'em to have thoſe few things that belonged to 'em, all they got by it was to hear his <hi>Excellency bolt out his Indignation</hi> againſt them in calling them Rebels, and commanding them from his Preſence.—</p>
            <p>I have thus moſt faithfully and as briefly as I could given a true Account of my preſent ſad Condition, whereby it appears I went to <hi>India</hi> in a Ship of the Companies, and ſtaid there with leave for which I paid 100 <hi>l.</hi> and as to my accepting an Employment in the King <hi>of Syam</hi>'s Service, I was not onely introduc'd to it by the Companies Chief and Council at <hi>Metchlepatam,</hi> but during all the time of my Continuance in that ſtation I held a friendly Correſpondence with the <hi>Preſident</hi> and ſome of the Chief of their Servants at <hi>Fort</hi> St. <hi>George</hi> yearly trading to that Port with my own Shipping which were always kindly receiv'd, and diſpatch'd tho they never had any other Paſſes than my Commiſſions to the Commanders and Supra Cargo's: and moreover, I was ſtill further confirm'd in my belief that my reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at <hi>Mergen</hi> was no way diſpleaſing, by peruſal of a kind Letter which the late King was pleas'd to honour my <hi>Lord Phaulkon</hi> with, wherein he does graciouſly condeſcend to acknowledge the great kindneſs my <hi>Lord</hi> had ſhewn his Subjects in that Kingdom, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the continuance thereof on aſſurance of his Royal favour to him in all Occaſions.— And after all this when his Command for my leaving that Place and Service, was made known to me by the <hi>Proclamation</hi> publiſh'd by Captain <hi>Weltden,</hi> I obey'd it with all duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſubmiſſion. I never ſhew'd the leaſt diſreſpect nor did the leaſt prejudice to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, but contrarily was ready on any Occaſion to do them the beſt Services that lay in my Power: yet what by their means I have loſt at <hi>Mergen</hi> and has ſince been taken from me by their Servants, is of no leſs value than 40000 <hi>l.</hi> eſcaping with my Life in an empty Veſſel, wherein I am come to throw my ſelf at the Feet of Juſtice, and implore relief againſt the Authors of theſe Oppreſſions.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Samuel White.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
